maybe a small startup running a private
program will will have like a small
cheese or a small set of holes but giant
companies has like a way bigger market
share so the cheese is big and there and
so there is more holes and that's how I
approach my targets right now the
metaphor works and I will fight anyone
that say otherwise
[Music]
[Applause]
all righty Richard what's on the docking
for today oh an ASMR ad say L I got you
I got you all right guys so today we're
gonna ah aack surface management roles
not as okay I got you well if we're
talking about attack surface management
then of course we're talking about the
ASD note team right the ogs in the ASM
space and this time around they've
released a new community project they're
attack surface management job board
place where you can see all of the
companies that are hiring for attack
surface management jobs so if you're
interested in that sort of thing if
you're a Recon heavy hacker or if you
just want to get your hands on the asset
noote product to play around with it um
then definitely check out that job board
that's going to be at asset
note. Asin note. ASMR I'm going to make
them change it to ASMR so so if you want
to support the Pod or if you want to
check out that job board head over to
asset note. ASMR all right back to the
show let's
go alrighty man here we are hey it's uh
it's been a fun week we are uh sitting
down right now in groby at Ronnie's
Studio here and exactly um I I came into
town for grak and uh
Ronnie I can't get the the the uh the r
correct but um Ronnie showed me an
excellent time and you know I had a plan
for this pod Ronnie but then you had a
plan as well for this pod I'm so sorry
no no I'm open to it I'm open to it man
we're just chilling so uh what were you
thinking yeah I I was thinking that um
like re re recently I've been uh helping
a friend of mine into getting into bugti
hunting and uh the interesting thing is
that from someone that is completely
beginner just a little bit passionate
about computers I I noticed like how
hard it is to get all the concepts that
we know today right and um and you did
like a great thread at the time on on
Twitter that that I I actually sent him
to him and I'm noticing how he's trying
to learn from your tread and I think
that beginners tutorials needs to be a
bit more hardcore you know I see I see
okay okay uh and so the goal is like um
face it in your thread the first thing
that comes to mind is like the web
fundamentals right and like how do you
restart into web what do you learn
exactly and there's so many you know
resources but I guess like the best ones
are the most technical ones and if you
start with the hardest one like the
RC uh the the mdn documentation stuff
like that you are going to get to the
roots and fundamentals of what is
really web and that will help you for
your bugy journey I'm going to go ahead
and pull up the the Tweet right here
we'll show it on the screen but
essentially it's it's just a description
of what I would do over the course of a
year if uh I was to try to go from zero
to 100K in bug Bounty and yeah web
fundamentals I think that's one of the
areas where I've gotten the most
questions yes you know is like what what
does a web fundamental you know
education include um so yeah we can talk
a little bit about that and I think also
you know this may be one of the episodes
the one of the rare episodes of critical
thinking that might be a little bit more
um beginner oriented but I think as more
advanced hackers as well it can be
helpful to reflect on these things not
only for the purposes of being able to
teach them to the next generation of
hackers but also as a as sort of a
reflection ourselves on on the basics
and uh and and what it looks like to
develop those Basics yeah um yeah
especially since we were talking about
like
availability that you saw an article
about uh on on GitHub uh where it's used
like the head uh verb HTTP verb as a as
a way to to exploit it and like it just
shows that sometimes you need to go back
to the roots and the basics and go way
deeper into the you know the
fundamentals of what is the technology
that the technology that you are trying
to hack and how like as an expert in the
field and how as a beginner you can go
straight to the you know yeah the the
root of that kind of technology in order
to restart your exploitation Journey
yeah and I think that's one of the
things that's really pivotal too about
learning um hacking because we we were
talking in that same uh conversation as
we were hiking up the mountain exactly
you know that when you hacking is sort
of a unique thing because it's not like
once you learn it you're good you know
like every single time we hack something
we are relearning you know we we have to
take that product that that application
or whatever and we have to break it down
just like we did in the beginning when
we were learning the skills for
hacking and uh and find the problems
with it um and so we can't really teach
hacking without teaching the ability to
learn uh the ability to learn an
application and and and that that whole
that whole flow um and and and I think
we can apply that as well you know we do
it every time we hack an application we
we do what we needed to do um you know
back in the day when we were just
starting uh except you know at that
point we're we're doing it against a
whole industry a whole a whole set of um
Technologies HTTP you know web browsers
that sort of thing um so it's a it's a
lot wider scale right you know you might
you might say it's the biggest uh set of
applications there might be out there
there um but essentially it's it's the
same principles just applied at a larger
scale and then at a smaller scale once
you sort of have the basic understanding
of what vulnerabilities exist on these
sort of attack surfaces yeah and there
is something that uh you are grasping
right now that I think a lot of
beginners but I know also a lot of re
expert people in the field that are
trying to get into bugy so bugy
beginners but already expert in cyber
security is that the ability to find the
good resources in order to help you
exploit some vulnerabilities like the
the question that we get the most in our
DMS is like okay where do I learn stuff
like how I I find the information and I
think this is a huge problem for us to
answer this one because the goal is not
to give the knowledge to someone it's
like to give the ability for them to
find their their own knowledge because
when you are going to to get like this
really weird technology that exists just
on Two web servers in the world you are
not going to get a Google search or
anyone on earth that is going to know it
right you need to go down into the
documentation the technical spec and
really understand it yourself and that's
how you re find the the the information
just trying to yeah to face uh the the
the most technical and root thing
and if we take your trade your trade the
fundamentals where when I'm trying to
teach someone and just give like them
the mdn documentation which is I would
say the beginner friendly version of
some RFC uh and then I I tell them like
to try this to find the same information
in the RFC uh that is more complete
right so when you are learning HTTP uh
it's great to actually learn what is
HTTP what it's built on top of so TCP uh
TCP IP uh uh how do you reach uh a
domain what is a host what's his an IP
and everything and like go to the root
fundamentals because sometimes in those
roots there is like some big
vulnerabilities yeah I mean that's
that's the kind of stuff you see with
James Kett all the time is he he's you
know sort of peeling back those layers
and addressing uh the vulnerabilities at
a lower level um yeah I think that's
definitely important I I think it's
difficult to give also resources like
like mdn or the RFC or whatever and say
like hey these are the the you know
source of Truth for these things because
at the end of the day like you said you
have to you have to go and find them you
know and uh and and so yeah absolutely
reading the RFC and the mdn is a really
great resource and and something that
that we should do um but there's also
going to be you know those random little
little forums out there you know with
some do some old Linux gezer you know
that that knows that was there when this
you know obscure protoc protocol was
created and you got to read that too and
so it's a lot of it's a lot of digging
and a lot of like you said you know not
necessarily being intimidated by these
um these highly technical documents
because at the end of the day this is
what I always tell myself you know when
I'm shaking in my boots in front of like
this you know very scary Target is like
at the end of the day somebody not that
much smarter than me probably you know
wrote this whole thing right right and
you know sure there there are some like
you know Mega genius people out there
that are just you know leagues above us
all but I feel like given enough time I
can I can uh you know compensate for the
difference you know so um you know
remembering that these people aren't
Gods you know that this is not something
beyond my my you know ability to grasp
we just have to put in the time to get
there um so yeah I think and then also
you know on the web fundamental
just going back to the nuts and bolts of
the web fundamentals I think um it's
hard to know where to draw the line on
those sort of things right like do I
need to know what every single header
does you know do I need to know what
every single object on window you know
in the JS engine of Google you know
Chrome chromium or whatever do I need to
know what all those means and and the
answer is no but it wouldn't hurt you
know you know like you know you can
always spend more time going down that
path and that's one of the reasons why
in this article I I outline or in the
Tweet thread um I outline this ratio of
hacking to learning where in the
beginning you're going to be spending
you know 80% of your time or more on
learning and and and but it's very
important to get that you know 20% 10%
of the time actually hacking so you know
where where things are making a
difference yeah and yeah that's actually
interesting thing like on like trying to
learn everything like where do you stop
like do you need every other and I think
like you need to learn enough to be able
to manipulate yourself the data and to
be able to find back where you can uh
learn uh the for instance like a
specific header uh you need to know
where in the documentation you can find
it back that's a good point yeah it's
not about learning like having like the
the strong knowledge of of the IFC it's
about trying to understand how you can
read the RFC in order to find back the
knowledge right um I think there there
is an Asin quote or at least many people
attribute that to Einstein are saying
like why why would you search uh
something like why would you know
something that that you can search for
right and I think it's true to some
degree like you need to understand the
overall concept like the abstract of it
but what the day you are going to need
to to get you know your hands dirtty you
need to find back where you you you
learn this from and in order to go even
deeper in this specific technology um
yeah that's one of the things I've
struggled with as well is like uh as far
as needing a good notes system for that
sort of thing right like I'll often
think I know I read an article where
there was like some similar technology
to this and I I just need to find that
now you know and I and I can't find it
no matter you know how well I Google
dork um and and for a little while I was
using like this Clipper um like the
Evernote uh Web Clipper or something
like that um but I I I've since stopped
using that and I feel like I need to
find a good solution for that again you
know to be able to reach back and grab
that but um yeah I guess what other
stuff do we need to cover in the web
fundamentals area I mean I guess one of
the the things I I always talk over with
the beginners is like what is actually
happening when you are you interacting
with a web server via your web browser
right yeah what I feel like even before
like
how it is interacting I feel that you
need to learn how you need to interact
yourself with with uh the the backend
system that you are trying to reach but
again I guess it's it's better curl yeah
using like Cur or maybe even a netcat or
something like netcat and like print F
yeah like like just for one single
reason how many times you sent a get
request on burp kaido or or any proxy
that you're using and you forgot the two
uh trailing lines the the the new lines
at the end yeah for sure 100% And when
you have like a system like curl or
netcat where it's really low level and
you control every part of it and you can
actually understand like what specific
header or what the paath is doing or
what the host is doing and just trying I
don't know try to reach Google with
netcat and and trying to do a redir or
something like that is actually
something good to learn because you are
controlling every part of uh of of your
request and I know like some really good
hackers uh that actually for request
smuggling do not use any proxy yeah
directly goes on like that yeah and and
I think having that lower level ability
to play around with the individual bites
is pretty useful for sure I I I've done
it I've done done it only a couple times
myself but I think it gives you
confidence as well that the system is
actually as simple as you think it is
you know like like I think there's
always this um like uh for me this sort
of like fog of yeah maybe like I think I
understand that but I haven't actually
like played around with it and got my
hands on it yet so I think there you
know there could be something that I
don't understand there and when you
actually like just netcat and print F
you know then it absolutely like you
know you know for sure oh I need to put
this new line I you know I need to do
that and and you see how granular the
control is that you have over all that
and that's also like this low level like
learning at the beginning those low
level stuff really going to help you in
the future to trust a tool or not like
that's that's a great Point your your
Reliance on the tool um like like this
is someone else that cated it for you
right and so you rely on that knowledge
and their coding skill and I mean of
course there is some amazing amazing
tools but sometimes you need something
like really specific and you don't know
if the tool is going to do it or not
like um myself at the really beginning
when Jim Kettle uh released the burp
extension for R smuggling you know I
just tried to run it everywh and I was
like hey it doesn't do anything it
doesn't find any viability but then I
got back with a net cat request and I
was like oh wait why the response is
like
that and and that's I I feel like as a
beginner I learned something good about
that I learned like what the the request
was and what that I was needed to to be
manipulated inside the request in order
to
reproduce availability right and uh yes
it's harder uh it's not for everyone but
I think it's a good advice even for
beginners or experts to just try to go
deeper in your stack and understand like
okay what am I doing right now like what
is really happening behind yeah you said
you're not even letting this poor kid
use a a web browser at this point right
like Ronnie is teaching this kid and as
we were walking up this mountain
Ronnie's like yeah man you know
breathing heavy The Briefing is accurate
you know I I I don't even let him use
use the browser at this point he's just
using curl I'm like the browser is going
to do so much things for you and uh I
want want him to actually learn like the
structure of the request and like for
instance if I don't put the right verb
what what the backend is supposed to to
answer to me and then I want him to go
on another system and see if he got the
same response because like something as
easy as a 302 it's like okay what's a
302 let's go on the mdn okay look at the
mdn read it and tell me what's the F2
doing oh it's a redir what's a redir uh
I don't know okay learn what's a r and
what's R okay apparently it's giving me
a path to go to can you find the path to
go to in the response it's like there's
nothing in the body I mean hey hey there
you go that's a good that's a good
Discovery and and that's and that's why
I told him use netcat see the full
request or curl with the dash eye and
they're like oh my God there is a
location header and like okay you see
and that's where I I I understood
something really um really important is
that the tool I are you know off
officiating a lot of what it is doing
and if you really want to learn web
fundamentals it's going to help you to
go to the documentation and just trying
to to you know to actually generate
yourself those lowlevel uh requests and
adding that vvv you know on getting the
actual raw you know hgp request based it
sounds like you know with this guy that
you're that you're working with you're
using a lot of the Socratic method sort
of like asking the question that he
needs to go find the answer to and and
and I think that's really helpful um and
it it also teaches him how to ask the
correct question for himself at at some
point down line um I'm just such a big
fan of that education model this the
Socratic method it it can be kind of a
pain in the ass like I'm sure this guy's
gonna punch you and the next time he
sees you in person but exactly I I I I
told him like uh if I think that the
question is not good enough I'm just
going to let him
enter himself right but if I know that I
struggled myself to to find the answer
I'm going to try to help him like find
the answer faster uh and I think that's
a good way to do because as I told him
at the beginning you need to be able to
face the wall yourself because I'm not
going to be there for your bugun career
and you can't rely on me and I don't
want to to collaborate with you in the
future
maybe let me be honest I don't I don't
want to collaborate with
you yeah I I I like to do my thing on my
side I got this guy r I love to
collaborate with him yeah he's a good
dude yeah yeah no that's good okay so we
got the HTTP sort of spec right the RFC
the mdn you've got um you know browser
internals I always I always uh think
it's really important for people to
understand how same origin policy works
and like the whole concept of you these
isolated origins in in the browser um
and why you can't just use JavaScript to
reach into an if frame and like grab
some data out unless it's a same origin
frame right and then you can um and then
understanding what sort of tools you
have at your disposal there especially
if you want to become a good client side
hacker because um so much of client side
hacking is just chaining together all
these little gadgets that you get into
making it into something that is really
impactful um let's see what else do we
have on the on the web fundamentals um
environment there yeah um like actual
structure of the of the back end could
also be helpful like proxies and and
what Frameworks are being used and that
sort of thing yeah I I was going to to
to mention that one because this is like
uh a huge part of what I'm also trying
to to teach the this kid right now uh is
that two different back ends is It's
Kind sound obvious but will not
implement the same standard in term of
uh of re request response right um I he
sent me a message and like hey I did
that option verb on that request and I
got a full three and like shouldn't be
option always uh give back all the
others and methods that I can reach yeah
yeah it's like hey maybe there is
something in front a layer or maybe they
did something custom and that's where
you you dig like this is like the hacker
mindset is like what happened and why it
is happening and how can I use that on
my in my advantage right that's a good
sign though I think for him you know
that he's like oh me try a different
HTTP verb here and he's identified an
htttp verb that is actually supposed to
like give you data about a specific
endpoint on how it you know how it works
um yeah that's that's a good that's a
good sign for our boy here you know I
think he's going down the right path and
and and the structure of the back end is
like such a good thing like I I'm glad
that you put it on the thread because
like just a reverse proxy will not
implement the same for instance uh RFC
than uh the the backend right uh and
just because there is like two type of
implementation it creates a confusion
and you can exploit that uh to your
advantage and it's like um a second
order P past traversal right it's the
the the the same philosophy the same
mindset is that you have two different
layers that are not treating data the
same way and we not talking like about a
specific viability specific technology
like this is an the abstract thinking of
it like you have several layers and you
are just trying to jump from one layer
to another and trying to see if
they look at the data uh differently
yeah that's a widely applicable concept
is the whole the whole um disagreement
on how data should be processed normally
in input from the user yeah um yeah so
so I guess there's like that set of
Technology right where you need to
understand the yeah maybe this was a
little bit of an area where that TW that
tweet was ing is like okay even though
we understand the
fundamentals um and maybe we understand
the individual vulnerabilities I think
there's some mindset things like you
were saying like Okay the overarching
principle of mismatch in parsing data or
the the uh Universal this is one we talk
about all the time the universal
principle of uh context breaks right
where we're breaking out and it can be
any context break right I I talk about
you know maybe the the most um benign
version of this is is when you have like
a cookie and and you're injecting into
the value of the cookie but you can also
specify the semicolon and and inject
into the um the the attributes of the
cookie right that's a context Break um
and we also see context breaks in you
know xss and all sorts of injection
based stuff um that that could be that's
something that I haven't seen people
really formula eyes or formal eyes even
in like a blog post of like what are
some of the overarching
hacker principles that you should have
in your mind that should start
triggering red flags yeah is yeah this
is we that's a good piece of that's a
good idea for a piece of content
actually for beginners I think so and
and that's what you know uh earlier
today Justin was uh struggling on the
puzzle uh yes I was I hate those
freaking puzzles dude yeah you know and
I think hiking is like much like a
puzzle like I totally disagree with that
I I think I think hacking is like very
different than a I'm sorry continue
continue I just I I hate these puzzles
so much and I feel so comfortable
hacking So when you say that my guttur
all response is like hell no yeah okay
but but hit me hit me I'm I'm going to
to finish the sentence it's it's much
like hacking in the like abstract layer
of thinking right you don't do not need
to first check what is happening like
that that's really how to formulate but
you don't need to to just stop at what
is is in front of you you just need to F
on the an abstract layer like okay what
is happening like how is my request
reaching the back end is there anything
in the middle and like if there is like
a
connection then there is a rule and this
is my rule this is my world okay and now
that I have my rule what I can I do to
break it and that's I feel like one of
the most
lowlevel um abstract thinking that you
can do like I I me at least for me right
like you create a rule and you say okay
my request is following this Rule now
how I or whatever yeah and how I can
cheat the game and once you have like
this abstract thinking you go down to
the technical layers until you write
your request to hack right yeah yeah
know that that does make sense and that
is I don't know man mapping it onto that
stupid freaking little game you know is
is where I have the problem with that
but I think the the overarching
principle does apply and uh it made me
think also of a another one of the
principles is is this whole concept of
time of check to time of use right like
like I love that security principle
where it's like okay you know there's
some security check that occurs at some
point that's trying to prevent you from
doing something and then after that
check
uh there that that data is is modified
in some way you know the classic example
for me where I think this really clicked
was like back in the day was um an
environment in which there was a check
being performed for a specific string
you know let's say it's script or
whatever trying to prevent cross
scripting and then right after that
there was a replace uh you know call
that would that would you know delete
something out right so you could do you
know uh you know open Open Bracket Sr
and then you know whatever it start
start the script tag again and then it
it would pull out that middle piece and
it would connect the two pieces together
right and so that that time of time of
check to time of use and then there
being some sort of modification in
between the check and the use um is
another one of those overarching
principles so maybe I should append that
tweet I think and and add some of these
on there as like general principles to
be on the lookout for yeah I I think
that's a really nice idea like trying to
to to create like category of abstract
thinking uh related to to
vulnerabilities like like even more
abstract than injection right like uh we
said secondary past traversal is just
because there's two layers that are not
agreeing on on what data uh how they
should pass the data right uh all the
the injection categories like we are
over tracing user input and we can like
this is a brainstorm right now yeah no
no no it's good it's good but like if we
try to break down the abstract thinking
uh while we are web hacking that could
help a lot people to to go like on
another kind of methodology because I I
feel like there is many different
methology there is one where you just um
check box everything like every kind of
vulnerabilities that that that you think
and maybe it's not efficient but some
people need that right and it's
completely like a rational methodology
to use especially like if you're like me
and you forget what you did earlier yeah
yeah for sure uh but then there is some
other people that live in their mind and
so creating like some kind of mind map
of what you think is happening and
trying to first check if your mind is
correct uh like for instance hey I think
there is like one reverse proxy allow
balancer and then I can reach the back
end but the back end is in the cluster
so I have different pods right how can I
check that and so you check that and
then okay that's my rules like I'm
involving in that world like this is my
mind
map and um and that helps a lot like
just being able to confirm that the
technology works in the way that you
think it is because you're like it's
like building these hypotheses and then
validating the assumptions along the way
yeah that that's I think that's a part
of the overarching process and then we
kind of apply these various tenants of
uh hacker mentality onto that So like um
another one that I just thought of
inspired by Kevin Mizu uh you know from
the the G hacks presentation um is this
whole concept of the mutation xss that
that that he presented um is the whole
concept of dealing with user input that
is supposed to be spec compliant in some
way and is not spec compliant so how do
we how do we deal with Messy input from
the user and get it back to a place
where we like it it needs to be rendered
or needs to be presented in a way that's
compliant with a specific specification
I think I think there's vulnerabilities
that could that that arise there pretty
often and and um yeah another one that
just that just comes to mind as well is
I think could be broadly categorized as
um like lack of depth U of understanding
the technology that you're using right
the the classic example that comes to
mind here is um uh
xxe right where you have this XML
language that is just supposed to be for
like marking up data and somehow there's
like this weird feature where you can
just run arbitrary code you know encode
inside of this whole language and then
you know you see that as well on top of
it with xslt and now it's like oh wow
this is a you know freaking turn
complete language that that's just built
in as a side component of XML and it's
like okay so you know there's there's so
many
recursive layers of technical dep um to
all these systems that we're using I
mean you see this with the dependency
confusion stuff too exactly yeah and I
really like what what you you just said
as an abstract abstract thinking like uh
developers misconception of a technology
or maybe more like more lack of uh root
knowledge uh and you see that with ssrf
vulnerabilities right so there is an
ssrf uh you manage to get your met data
endpoint there is a fix what's the fix
okay I'm going to just forbid uh the
metadata endpoint yeah but there is DNS
okay I'm working on another layer okay
I'm just going to forbid any I do a DNS
resolution and forbid any that resolve
to uh to that specific IP yes but an IP
is uh just
128 bytes yeah and but the RFC doesn't
say how you can represent that there is
a convention to represent that with the
four dots uh but you can also represent
that in exod simal and in decimal okay
so you just bypassed uh the the check
you've got the DNS rebinding and then
you've got so many technical layers
technical depth layers and I think if
you specialize in even one of these
um you know High overarching
methodologies then you can get a lot of
vulnerabilities out of it right like
with these sort of things but being able
to apply all of these across a a Target
I think is what kind of gives you more
of an edge as a as a hacker where you
feel like um you you get to this point
where you're like yeah you know given
enough time I can probably find a vul on
pretty much anything you know yeah um
and I think that's what a lot of people
are shooting for and one question that a
lot of beginners also ask a lot in our
DMs I think is okay re re really great
advice yeah I should go look at root
things and then apply them to to my t
but what do I aim for like what's the
weird thing that I should aim for and I
guess that the answer is like you
shouldn't start with research uh you
should start with maybe someone else's
research and that's an advice from Jeff
Kettle like uh I think the article is
named uh Hey so you want to be a web
security researcher or something like
that don't remember the exact name but
he says like hun for forgot forgotten
knowledge so basically take the blog
post of someone that you re understood
or really like the technique and you
found it elegant and you know you Vibe
with the technique and you're like okay
I'm going to try to First apply this
technique on all the targets that I I
know and I like and I'm like okay what
works and what doesn't work and why it
doesn't work and when you apply
something at scale you are going to see
all the edge cases and that's where your
research starting that's really good
that's that's some really good data
right there yeah so and I say that
because that's how I I I started uh
backb I was struggling for six months
like I feel like like this was the
everyone's beginner story right you do
not find any varability you try your
checklist you try everything but
everyone tried the the same thing and
you get like a Jed open redirect and you
are like at this close to to just
abandon bti and then I was like okay
let's go to a technology that is widely
used uh but maybe people are not looking
to into and I went to Wordpress plugins
and I was like I go to all the targets
that are on ha one and check which one
use WordPress so you learn a little bit
of Recon there but just enough to have
like maybe 1,000 websit or maybe even
less right and then you just check
enumerate like all all the plugins and I
was just aiming at the the the the
smallest plugins right and I was just
checking hey is there an xss that
already exists on the plug-in and
usually like like checking for cves
against it or you saying like actually
doing source code review yeah no maybe
at the beginning you just check like if
there is a a CV if there is a CV you
have a a quick win and if there was a CV
you check the fix of of the CV and so
you start little bit of code review and
you're like hey I managed to find my xss
that's another one of the that's another
one of the overarching principles is the
the fix yeah right like checking
checking the fix at a granular level um
and making sure that it's it's fully
technically validated I like that and
and so for that WordPress research it
wasn't like a huge research but it was
like a little bit of of code review and
everything and one day I was doing my
excess thingy I was doing a couple of
hundred bucks uh like up to 1,000 and I
got to a point where hey this xss is not
working on this specific website like it
works on my doer environment of
WordPress but doesn't work on the
website and that's where you start
learning really it's like what's the
difference what
CSP exactly when you learn what CSP is
yeah and so you start another Deep dive
and then that's where the research start
and just applying a research at a bit of
a larger scale just trying the same
technique really Niche technique and
then trying to see all the edge cases
from the edge cases learn how you create
your own research that's in my opinion
how you can become like a good bugy
Hunter yeah that that at scale piece I
think is really is really interesting
that that hasn't been an approach that I
I think I've implemented a lot but I I
have seen that the edge case just you
know back in the day when I was doing
more Recon
automation you're absolutely right right
as as soon as you try to do something at
scale those edge cases are going to
stick out like a sore thumb right cuz
they're just going to break your whole
system and it's going to be like oh why
is this actually not working um so that
is a good way to to find all those
little tiny little tweaks off the off
the edge of what you would normally
expect and and that's why sometimes I I
don't rely on On Tools where I start the
research I prefer to write my own really
buggy tool like in terms of of finding
stuff like it doesn't sorry it doesn't
find like good findings there result of
false positives but I like to learn why
it is a false positiv right and if it's
just a blat and false positive I'm going
to fix it but then there is like those
edge cases like imagine you are writing
an xss finder tool a kaido Plugin or
something and then you just check if
there is a reflection right and you're
like oh okay I got my reflection then
there is xss right and then you
understand oh but there is some tags
where like it doesn't it doesn't pass as
HTML
and so you're like wait but can I
actually still get xss on those tags and
then you go deeper and deeper into the
documentation you go back to the RFC you
go back to the HTML mdn documentation
and you are like trying to understand
like this freaking tag what it is doing
because it never used since 2008 right
it was just an obscure browser that
introduced that and that and that
company sounds like a very specific uh
problem
talking about last eight hours of my my
time yeah dude that was three years ago
I think that's a really interesting
piece though too because when I was
giving the workshop at gack um I kind of
said one of the I think one of the
problems with hackers is that we often
reinvent the wheel time and time again
we make the same tools and why do we
rebuild a time and time again it's
because we don't trust the
implementation of other hackers because
it's opaque in a lot of scenarios and I
say it's opaque you know the source code
would still be there but it's like oh
okay I've got to you know sort through
all of this source code to make sure
that it's properly implementing um you
know my methodology of this is how I
would you know bypass a 403 or you know
look for an fuzz for an xss in a
specific scenario right and so
essentially what we end up doing is then
we end up writing the code ourselves so
that we know this is this is how it
should be implemented right um because
we're we're essentially taking our own
methodology and uh trying to automate it
right and build it out so you can
definitely see the various edge cases
pretty well that way um yeah but but I
think it's not always that that piece of
I don't have introspection into the tool
it's also oh I want to understand this
more thoroughly by automating it yeah
and that's that's uh that's a good
principle and something that yeah maybe
a lot of the beginners should take a
look at yeah and that that speaks also
to the should the beginner hacker know
how to program y uh piece of that how
much time do you think hackers should
spend on building a some sort of ability
in you know JavaScript python you know
some sort of client side or like
scripting language let's let's call it a
scripting language versus a programming
language oh that's that that's that's an
entire debate here um but I mean to do
this methodology that we just described
it's necessary right especially with the
onset of AI I think it's a little bit
tricky right because you can definitely
get away nowadays with you know
prompting in natural language and then
being able to read code yeah I think so
I I think it's probably not necessary
even if you're looking to
um even if you're looking to build that
skill set in the way of of automating
you know something to understand it a
little bit better you can often times do
that via natural language prompting and
then just modification yeah I I I
think you it's not NE as a Bug Hunter to
like code really well but it it it's
better if you code actually I I I have
like in in my mind an entire debate
because I think like I I know some
hackers that do not know how to code at
all right uh but they are finding like
some really crazy vulnerabilities
because they don't have the barrier of
thinking a developer might have
implemented something yeah and and
thinking oh you know a developer
couldn't have been this stupid you know
to implement it this way yes they could
have yeah or or or even like just try
some super naive and obscure thingy and
just say because they don't know that
normally it doesn't happen and just
because they don't know it they're going
to test it and it kind of worked once
you know um I feel like that hurts them
more than it helps them though because
I've seen that a couple times before and
I've been like oh yeah you know they
tried that and then they kind of got
lucky right but then you know how much
time do the does that person spend
trying things that will just not work
yeah you know like and I and I know for
a fact that it will not work yeah and
and and that's the other side of of my
of my debate like saying okay but when
you're are going to learn you are going
to learn the concept and you are indeed
going to reduce the things that you are
going to try because you think that
people are implementing code that way
but also by knowing more code and I
think it brings a lot more value because
indeed you can automate those scripts
and and and be able to script at least a
little bit will reduce the friction okay
okay so so going going back to that
though I guess putting the the scripting
thing aside we're all that guy that
doesn't know that a little a little bit
right that doesn't know how to script a
little bit right because at the end of
the day we each have our own blind spots
for what kind of tech technology we're
proficient with or that we're familiar
with in any way shape or form so when
we're building out this like the rules
like you were talking about the rules of
the environment that we're that we're in
we can make assumptions on okay well you
know I see this and this which tells me
it's probably a reverse proxy but you
know you don't know that for certain and
that's the that's that's the cool part I
think about bug Bounty because bug
Bounty takes a bunch of Hackers from a
bunch of different spots that all have
different eyes and different history and
different background and different
understanding of various technical
components and put it all together
because sometimes you need the dude
that's gonna you know assume that you
know this is the environment and that my
assumption is correct and we go super
technically deep and we try this really
obscure thing that would only work if my
my understanding of the stack is 100%
correct and then you also have this guy
that's like what if I just put a little
tick here I wonder you know what that
does or you know just tries all of these
naive techniques to get the full
coverage and I think you need to be both
those guys like this is the answer that
you need to be both of those guys yeah
oh my gosh yeah yeah you you need to
learn but sometime you need like when
nothing works and you really want to
find a verb on the Target and before
like you know again you you you've
thought maybe on on a podcast or on a
conference or something where that that
I've seen that you like to learn uh a
Target until you cannot stand it anymore
right you want to learn the the
JavaScript until you are you know going
about the Javas expert on that specific
application is what I normally say and I
think that in my opinion before doing
that there is like uh the the the naive
part that should you should try it first
like the okay imagine I know nothing
about anything like I need to at least
try some stuff before uh getting more in
depth and then go back even after the
inep part go back and just say okay I'm
naive again but I know a bit more what
if I tried that then
and it's not about luck or anything it's
like sometimes you are so in in a tunnel
that you can't see the B bigger picture
right and just take take a step back and
trying to avoid putting buyers in your
mind because you became an expert on
that specific Target and like think I
know everything right you take a step
back being a naive again and you say but
maybe they just did that and uh I think
it it help so that's where we hacking
yeah right yeah I think so too so so
we've covered a little bit of like how
do we get the technical knowledge we've
covered a little bit of uh abstract you
know sort of highlevel principles about
um hacking and one of the things that I
think is a hard skill to teach and some
people just have it straight from the
beginning and some people don't is this
whole concept of threat modeling it is
understanding where the boundaries are
in an application and um sort of getting
those in your brain and figuring out a
way to work around them and I've got
this friend actually you know him he's
uh he he's come to some live hacking
events with me and you know I I'll say
this you know his his technical piece is
not there he's he's he's not a IT guy
right but um the instant that I talk to
him you know he comes up with these
scenarios and he gets excited about the
scenarios too he's like what if we could
do this because I read this here and I
read this here and I said well you know
what what if this happened that would be
bad for the application right and he
just has that even without the technical
piece he has that whole understanding of
like this is how I pretend to be an
attacker and what would an attacker want
to do to this application and that just
came so naturally um to him and I and
I've definitely come up against some
people where it's like yeah I tried xss
I tried SE surf you know I don't know
what to do you know and it's like okay
well you got to think outside the box a
little bit here and you got to like
think about the actual trust boundaries
that are not necessarily a part of the
tech technology right that's what we see
with Seas Surf and xss right we're
dealing with a web browser we're dealing
with HTTP so there is a possibility of
access ass and there's a possibility of
Cerf but we're also dealing with another
layer of uh you know complexity as far
as the technology goes that implements
some business case and that's also a
system that's also a system that we can
abuse right that that's not you know
this technology and so um I guess
business logic vulnerabilities I think
are just such a massive category of
vulnerability that um threat modeling
that getting that skill of threat
modeling massively applies to did have
you approached this at all with your
with your with your um menty of sorts
and I don't know how do you think people
can address and build that threat
modeling skill yeah so when I was a
beginner someone told me an advice is
was like the Vol that you trying to find
uh try to think how much uh on the dark
net people will buy
it right yeah that's a very uh Simple
Solution but yeah that's a good point
and I I want to go a little bit
fur that's that's beautiful I love that
yeah and I thought that it was such a
great advice because then I I was like
yeah I understand why the xss on this
obscure website with no sop or anything
is not business relevant actually right
because there's nothing that you can
actually do to harm the customers or
anything and then once you understand
like not even the business logic
vulnerabilities but also the business
model of the company like what they are
selling and what what are their value as
a company then you need to aim on that
value right that's something that I wish
companies would be a little bit more
clear about you know I wish they'd be
more clear about their threat model too
but some companies it's like man if you
get access to any customer information
it's like the end of the world yeah and
some companies it's like oh wow if you
circumvent my whole payment model it's
the end of the world and and then some
companies it's like oh I don't care if
you circumvent circumvented my whole
payment model all I care about is
avoiding fines for gdpr you know like
it's it's nuts and and you know what
maybe it's a huge heart take but I
understand like sometime on Fortune
hundred companies that bypassing the the
their pricing model is not AV avability
because most of the companies like their
business model is relying on ads so on
the data that they manage to acquire on
on their users right and so this if
there is a leak of data is basically as
if you were you were managing to bypass
their business model but if you manage
to find one of their tools uh that cost
like my $5 a month and you manage to
bypass
that this is not like the biggest
vulnerability for them it's it's a it's
a it's a risk you know it's a payoff
thing for them too it's a business to
ision at the end of the day right is
like we accept this risk or we assign
you know a $300,000 a year developer
total comp developer you know four hours
to to uh actually fix this vulnerability
and okay how much money do that just
cost me versus like okay you know roon
gets free you know Slurpees for life or
something like that I I don't know you
know um like imagine e-commerce platform
you bypass uh the the the the you bypass
the payment huge deal because this is
their business model they're like they
they're actually selling stuff right but
then you go to I don't know like a a
company that has a a a license but uh
it's not actually their mainstream of
Revenue you bypass the the payment
they're not doing any Revenue anyway on
that specific piece and it doesn't cost
them anything so it's not like a huge
vulnerability for them and once you
understand the business model I'm not
saying like they're right to not pay you
or downgrade you I'm just saying once
that you understand like the Bas model
of the company that is rning like how
they make money and you can threat that
specific part then you you can do better
business model like a threat model that
will if you find business logic erors
yeah I I I get that that that does make
sense there's lots of there's lots of
nuance to that situation but I think
there's also this piece of that isn't
always how bug Bounty works right like
some of the people that have made the
most money in bug Bounty are not the
ones whose vulnerabilities will be sold
the for the most on the dark web right
they're they're the ones who have
learned how to game the system and there
are bug bounty hunters that just want to
establish a baseline freedom in their
life right so this is one of the things
that I kind of talk about my with my
mentees as well is like what is your
goal for bug Bounty as a part of your as
a part of your life right do you love
the the aspect of like let's dive deep
and let's do security research and would
you be doing that if you you know
weren't getting paid for it anyway and
that's where I think a lot of uh you
know really successful bug bounty
hunters come from but then there's also
this other side of like no actually I
just want to be able to be a digital
Nomad right and that's totally okay you
know like I'm not going to try to shame
the people that that are just wanting to
get back a portion of their life right
because I I I take you know I have that
you know I'm I'm self-employed I'm
full-time Bounty and I love every
freaking second of it and I totally
recommend to anybody who thinks they can
go fulltime Buck Bounty and pull it off
to do it because it's like super freeing
um and I think in in in those scenarios
it's like okay well I don't necessarily
need to um make a ton of money or get
these super technical uh you know
vulnerabilities I just need to
understand how to how to game the system
enough how to add enough value to the
right people who are willing to pay for
it to you know get my get the freedom or
whatever and and I do respect those
programs that that will pay for
vulnerability even if it's not like
something that is actively exploitable
just in the name of cleaning up their
attack surface yeah and I I want to to
cycle back on the on something that you
said is really interesting is that um
what is your bugman goal right and mo
most of the beginners like I think that
there was a haor report about that I
don't have like the exact numbers but
but um most of the beginners are here
because they want to actually prove that
they have enough technical knowledge to
to get a job right and that's how I used
bu actually good point that that's how I
used bu in order to get a job because I
didn't went to to college I'm really bad
at classes learning or anything like
scholar right and so I was like hey I'm
allowed to hack companies and they're
willing to to pay for it in a legal uh
fashion right and so I should use that
as my way of writing my own
resume and your approach on buun will be
different if when you think like that
than when your goal is to actually have
like a streamline of Revenue because
here you want to find like that n
vulnerability your Golden Goose that you
can milk until you get another Golden
Goose once it's expired but then um once
the Golden Goose is expired I like that
it's G you know it's a little bit uh
it's like the bagette we bought at the
store yesterday exactly I I I think you
know exactly what kind of
vulnerabilities I'm talking about right
here I do I do exactly what you're
talking about um and then there is the
goal of living off of it or the goal of
just having fun and the way that you see
back is going to um change the way you
are going to do the research of the
methodology right um like if you are
spending two hours a week uh in bti you
want to find the vulnerability if you're
spending like maybe I don't know 20
hours a week but you're a beginner that
just want to learn how stuff works then
you don't necessarily want to find a
varability you just want to actually
understand how other people managing to
hike into those kind of companies and
and yeah this will adjust your
methodology too I guess yeah for me I
think I allow myself to get distracted
from this a little bit right because for
a long time for me it was like and I
guess to a degree as a full-time Hunter
this is still the case but um I I I was
focused on the monetary aspect of it is
like oh well you know I can make a
full-time living off of this and I get
this complete freedom in my life and
that's great I love that you know and
and I and I do still have that to a
degree but I think I would really I
really care more now about
doing like more technical work you know
in-depth technical work and I allow
myself to get distracted by
really good monetary opportunities or
maybe you know I guess maybe I should be
honest with myself maybe I
care it's thanks for the therapy right
now Ronnie I appreciate it man I think
maybe I should be honest with myself and
like and say I actually do care about
the the financial aspect of it but that
I think is stemming from a place of um
habit you know whereas like at this
point I I don't necessarily need to keep
grinding on theone money aspect of it I
could focus more on the security aspect
and and the technical aspect and get
more fulfillment out of the whole thing
um but I still see these opportunities
uh popping up where I'm like oh you know
that seems like a good you know
opportunity to make some good money um
yeah so I think as you move through this
different stages of your life as a Bug
Hunter your goals may change for it as
well and that's something you got to be
aware of and and this is also going to
change like the targets you are going to
hack on right um yeah for instance when
I was a beginner it was okay any Target
where I can find something yeah exactly
what's the softest Target I can find how
many qu times have we been asked that
question you
know and and so I as I had like this uh
fantasy that private programs you find
more V abilities and then the the more
advanced I got into black buy then I
understood hey those big giant companies
up there they had like huge attack
surface and there is not enough people
to look at everything that they're
exposing on on the web right and so my
hunting change like the target Chang to
more like those kind of companies that
work in a system where there is like 15
principal Engineers or distinguished
Engineers or stuff like that
distinguished Engineers dude I want that
title distinguished engineer it's a
title that exists is it really heard
that yeah yeah no it exists I'm not
going to drop the company name but and
uh and where you need to have a process
of 15 people approving a project or a
fix right and that kind of company has a
way to exposing stuff on the internet uh
that are way different that the smaller
companies that run the private programs
and when I understood that I'm like hey
there is this is like you know
gries we are in France oh my God talking
about cheese I talked about cheese so
much this week I I have never talked
about cheese as much as I have in this
past week yeah that's a good point yeah
um like guer is a cheese with holes
right just you need to put that in
context some people don't have that in
the part of the world I guess god dude
no okay so it's tell me about the cheese
yeah and so maybe a small startup
running a private program will will have
like a small cheese so a small set of
holes but giant companies has like a way
bigger Market sh so the cheese is big
and they and so there is more holes and
that's how I approach my targets right
now the metaphor works and I will fight
anyone that say other way so the cheese
is Big he says yeah oh my God Ronnie
what are you this is amazing I love
getting the insight into your French
mind every company for me is a cheese
you know but I mean there is truth to it
in the fact that like you understand
that there there is way more processes
there there is a continuous development
so it means that one feature will get
redeployed uh maybe 20 times in a day
and with different uh code and when
you're are targeting those kind of
companies that really streamline a lot
of code you know that you can come back
H let's say on Google Drive you can come
back every day and every day there is a
new request a new feature a new thing in
the JavaScript that you didn't managed
to hack and so this is where I I think I
came like I was like a beginner and I
transformed to a more advanced hunter
because I knew the processes of those
companies and I knew that uh those were
the companies I wanted to Target and so
this reduced the set of like all those
amazing companies that are on ha one b
or any platform like and you don't know
which one to choose and then it reduced
to like I have 30 companies that I want
to H I'm in the same boat with you man I
mean I I mostly just go after those
bigger companies that are pushing code
constantly as well but I mean not to say
that the smaller companies aren't
pushing code constantly I think that
they are as well but um you know when I
was talking with Douglas day he's he's
got a different approach he just goes to
each one of these uh little small
programs and with 2K crits and just you
know spends four hours you know on each
one of them until he finds one that's
like oh wow this is really messed up you
know and and then just you know finds a
bunch of vones on those and so I think
it's it's not a one-size fits-all sort
of thing right it's like a per hacker
yeah and and and that was like the the
beginning of the thought I guess is that
depending on your goal and uh your bugy
goal you are going to approach the
targets differently like for instance
there is those amazing Recon Masters
right their target is not like one
company the target is like the the
entire list of a bti platform right and
they're running the automation on
everything and then there is those you
know FRS Rosen kind of hunters that are
like what is the funniest vulnerability
I can find in the world right
now correlation IDs oh my God man that
was such a crazy drop when he when he
hit us with that um and like those
approach are all valid but they have
different goals in mind one is to do
quantity the other one is to do quality
and both of them will get like a lot of
Revenue by the end of the day um but you
might have a diff like programs might
have a different perception on on you
like some programs will if you're like
this big Recon Master they will see you
as uh maybe an automation scanner that
is just pinging them like once a week
you know but there is other programs
like when you are like this amazing
hacker they are just going to see one
report a year but they're going to have
a sweat on the on the brow yeah I and
man I want to be the one where it's like
yo you get a report from from this and
it's like oh [__] you know or or or you
build a a deeper relationship with the
program as well and and like they're
like sup dude nice report you know just
finishing up the one last week that you
sent us you know that sort of thing I
think that's pretty that's a fun part of
bug Bounty for me and this human that
you say create the Deep connection you
need to know which with which program
you can actually create that because
once you understand the process on them
getting the vulnerability like some
programs have like their own dashboard
and they are just being fed by bti
platform and they are not see they are
not even seeing your name on the
dashboard you are just like a number
cares about the reporter name yeah you
are just a number and then there is the
overall dashboard seeing a trend of like
oh we got more V abilities but we fixed
those and like they are like okay we
happy about that but then there is the
programs that are like hey you remember
when you sent that vulnerability two
years ago uh well we want more we loved
that report we have it framed in our
office you ex yeah those are those are
great man those are great and and that's
just about processes because for
instance those bigger companies will
have stronger processes and they want to
scale they want to scale everything and
when you scale you remove the human side
and so you cannot create this deeper
connection and I think that as a
beginner you need a a deep connection to
learn bugti with the people like you are
working with right with the people
you're are sending reports because they
can give you the feedback that you
really need yeah that's the feedback
piece the feed that feedback piece is
really important and the the feedback
cycle I think is one of the things that
I really liked about bugb in the
beginning but it's getting a little bit
more challenging now as things are
becoming a little bit more volatile
where you know there's so volume coming
in that the triers are like just you
know kicking stuff that that are valid
reports and you start thinking ah is it
my methodology that's that's messing up
if you're a beginner you know or is it
or is it you know them not seeing this
vulnerability from a technical
perspective and uh it's hard it's hard
to say nowadays really and that's why I
get a lot of actually get a lot of
reports where people will ping me and
they'll be like hey um I reported this
bug and here's the bug uh and they Nate
it
and or or like informative did and I'm
like and I always try to look at those
and give them a little bit of a sanity
check right like and this is not I'm not
volunteering this by the way like like
like I can't get to all of them okay
[__] I'm I made a mistake to say that on
the podcast I kind of I kind of forgot
you know because I'm just sitting here
talking but um you know I I try to look
at those and I try to give them like
yeah you're crazy or no you're not crazy
that's like a valid vain then you need
to start mediation or whatever um
because it's hard in the beginning to
identify whether you have correctly
implemented some of these things you're
trying to learn or whether um you know
you're missing something or whether it's
the triager um most of the time it's the
hacker just to be clear but I think
there there are mistakes that happen for
sure yeah and uh I feel that most [__]
I'm gonna get please listen please guys
don't don't do this to me please but I
feel that also must time when I saw that
this is the hacker is because there was
a misconception of what the company was
actually running like how how the
company uh was actually running like for
for instance I have like someone that
that came to me like IRL right I'm not
like answer a lot of my DMs but um in
real life and they told me yeah I sent a
v to to Snapchat uh but they did they
said that it was informative I was like
okay hit me what was the vity is like um
well you see that when you take a
screenshot on on Snapchat it sends a
notification uh to the to the other
person right uh but they deployed the
web app and uh it wasn't
necessarily the same thing okay yes
sending a screenshot and I was like yeah
but what's the difference with you just
taking you know a picture with your
phone with another phone of your screen
they were like a man that's true because
that's not like what Snapchat is trying
to like like this is not like critical
yeah they're trying to add friction to
that to that piece right it's not
necessarily a security boundry exct
those are tricky th those sort of
vulnerabilities are you know
vulnerabilities outp putting quotes are
really tricky because you you think
you've correctly identify the threat
model and there may even be features you
know but really at the end of the day
they're like hey we know it's possible
we're just trying to make it less fun or
less easy for people to do stuff those
are those are hard yeah and and for for
for instance like really beginner
vulnerability that I found was like uh
you could bypass a checkbox right where
it was on an adult site and uh and you
needed to say uh I agree to those and
those and those and I saw that the
request in the back end was accepting
that you could not agree and so in the
back end it was reflected that I didn't
agree right and I was like there is a
logic problem in that request and there
there is logically right and so I sent a
report and that's where I got the best
program response because from the adult
adult entertainment site I love that
yeah and and because they didn't tell me
like this is informative I'm sorry they
explained exactly why it is informative
and they told me what's the difference
between you changing the request and
saying to the back end that uh you you
are not agreeing with those policies and
you agreeing with those policies but
just
lying and I'm like
yeah that doesn't make any sense and I
respectfully said yeah I'm dumb you
know it's a lesson we all have to learn
I think exactly yeah it is funny though
when you bypass those and it does
reflect it in the back end as well and
it's like no they didn't agree but we're
not going to stop asking him anymore you
know like and and it's interesting I've
always wondered about the um legal
implication yeah the legal implications
of something like that right like if if
I were to sue them and they were to look
in their system and it be like no he
declined the terms of conditions you
know and it's like yeah [__] you know
you know why don't we let them use the
app but then they can argue that the
only way to decline is to actually put a
reverse proxy and so this is some kind
of reverse engineering and you know
there's no threat model there for sure
but uh there the the thing where you
think that the the company like you have
the company's fight model right and we
we have been talking about that like
there is only the company's flight model
but then there is something that we
often forget there is the state fat
model uh which is like all the laws that
applicable and I saw a bug hunter that
just found that there was a company that
is something unlawful because of a
technical vity that was quite like
something really similar it was just
sending a request and then sending
another request and it was doing
something like regulatory that if you do
twice it's illegal for a company to do
I've seen this too yeah this is crazy I
think we were at the same uh event yeah
and they got like a major critical
Bounty because the company got could
have get in a lot of trouble by the
state uh and this is like another threat
model is like if you're targeting a
European company and they say oh no your
P p2i Mass p2i leak is just a medium
because you have a name first name email
and that's it it's like yeah but gdpr
gdpr is disagrees gdpr says that those
data are pii data and they're like yeah
but they're not relevant Pi data and
then you understand that pii means that
the more data points you have the more
identifiable someone is and so if in
your subset of data there is at least
like many European uh customers that can
be identifi identified to certain
location because of the data points then
there there is a a a bridge yeah man I
like that concept of like let's
brainstorm a little bit on what other
type of threat models there can be so
there's like the threat model for the
actual company themselves there's a
threat model for like the locality or
the region right if you're in the the EU
it's going to be different than other
places you are in the world and then one
that sort of came to mind as you were
saying that was the threat model of the
actual end user as well where you know
you've got these uh companies that are
providing like B2B services and there's
some or even if it's not necessarily
always B2B but there is like a B2B
component of it right um and then and
there's some sort of Integrations with
these like if you can affect via the
target you're trying to hack their B2B
customers um sort of
infrastructure that that may not may
have a they may not have a giant impact
on the actual company but it does have
an impact on their customers that that
can be a massive uh threat model that's
overlooked a lot of the time yeah I I
really like this and and I think that
this is also part of the abstract
thinking right where you you go to a
mind map and you're trying to check all
the different layers that could be
applied to uh to to a fat model to a
vulnerability or to everything so that
that's what when I was saying like
hacking feel like between me for as a as
a puzzle because you just need to forget
about what you see and you think on
another layer new a new paradigm right
where you are trying to just find all
the layers and the interconnection and
just say okay what can go deeply wrong
with the set of rules that is imposed
yeah xss is another example of this
right where xss is actually and this is
why you have the scope changed sort of
aspect in CVSs is the xss actually
affects the user's browser right it
doesn't actually affect the website it
affects the state in the in the in the
user browser um and if there wasn't a
browser there wouldn't be a
vulnerability here because you know that
HTML isn't actually being rendered and
it's not doing anything um yeah so
there's that component there's there's
like that that end user component
there's like this third party component
there's the state level component
there's lots of various components to
threat modeling for all these complex
applications yeah and there is also like
uh the part that is exposed but there is
also everything that is happening into
Al inside the company and that we think
that it's a blackbox but there is
actually so many little interactions
that end up being on the internet like
software supply chain attacks uh for
instance yeah yeah the software
development life cycle yeah that's a
great Point yeah def cups oh you can
have like all your developers one day
just putting your code base on GitHub
and like no one notice that and I'm not
going to say the company but there is a
company where there is active Developers
because there are like 40,000 employees
in the world or something like that
where they're actively pouring internal
source code on GitHub and there is no
keys or or anything to look at but you
just have like internal system
knowledge I love that so much yeah and
and and and that's another way of you
know thinking about everything if you
have a mind map of this is the where the
company sits and this is like the the
the the country the region uh and this
is like all the threat model and then
you zoom inside the company and you're
like okay there is that number of
employees this is the technical stack
there this is maybe they are raising
they they're doing a fundraiser right
now what can investors doing a
fundraiser yeah they're raising a yeah
yeah sorry raising funds yeah yeah
raising funds investment round there we
go yeah investment brand so what what
the investors can get scared about and
then you zoom little bit you're like
this is the technical stack you zoom you
zoom you zoom and so you mind map
everything and that's how I think we
need to approach B buy is about yeah
abstract thinking of all the threat
models you need a company who's on board
for that because there aren't a lot of
companies that will say yeah just
anything that affects us you know we
want to know about right you see you
have a couple of those but not not all
of them I love that piece of Epic Games
scope is like yeah anything else that we
own and you can prove it yeah we'll pay
for that yeah you know that's that's
that's pretty great yeah that that whole
overarching principle of looking at
those lost components of the software
development life cycle you know these
internal ticketing applications um the
correlation ID stuff with the logging in
introspection how does the how does the
sock how does the blue team actually
investigate these incidents a as they're
occurring and what sort of hindrances
can you put into play or or you know how
can you leverage that
that investigation um to to trigger
other vulnerabilities um and as a
beginner that can feel so overwhelming
right and I I think yeah we kind of got
off off the sorry sorry beginners that
are trying to listen to this and
thinking like holy [__] there's a ton of
things I don't understand no no because
I think this should be like some kind of
nor style like to be able to understand
that many layers but you need to start
with the layer you are most comfortable
with and more than comfort is like the
one that sounds the most interesting to
you right
uh again as the beginner when I was
starting like the the most interesting
thing at the time was xss like so many
beginners and then there was like the
reest smuggling and I was like what is
that it's so interesting it's so elegant
and so I wanted to find request
smuggling and uh and then I learned from
that and even all the knowledge that do
add up in a Varity sometime someday you
are going to go on an obscure
application and you are going to to say
damn this thing that I learned like four
years ago is going to be useful today
and um I feel this happened to me uh
recently uh like like I was working with
schow me and he did a a blog post about
that where he just pinged me on Discord
and he was like Hey I have like this uh
I think it was 40 character hash and I
have the feeling that is predictable uh
we should you know break it and so the
first eight chars were were a time stamp
and then there everything felt so random
and I advise you to to read the article
but the way I was thinking about this
breaking was like a technique that
learned like four years ago on an
obscure CTF and where there were like
okay let's guess what the hash is doing
like how I what what is computed and
just trying like different methodologies
until you get the right prediction
pattern right and because I read that
four years ago I was like oh maybe I can
find it back and get their methodology
and never used it in four years but the
knowledge was useful at some point so
everything you do to learn something
will be a payoff even if you don't find
intertwines into other things down the
line for sure all right man what what
what else do we have on on this beginner
front we didn't really cover uh the the
Tweet like we actually plan to here I
guess um we the Tweet actually says okay
web fundamentals and then we go into a
different set of of you know various um
kind of pH classes as we move into month
three four 5 six and then uh yeah 6
through eight we're doing code review
and actually de veloping sort of our
speciality as a as a hacker um yeah I
think the I I think that piece of
understanding these various vul patterns
like xss and curf and that sort of thing
those have a couple really solid
purposes right they teach you those V
classes which you see you know on lots
of targets so you can just apply it
directly but they also um apply some of
those higher principles like we kind of
like we talked about of oh injection
okay injection is this concept that I
need to apply more widely and I think we
you kind of get that through osmosis as
well you know it's not necessarily
something you're studying and being like
Oh yeah okay context breaks that makes
sense it's more of like oh okay that's
what context breaks looks like actually
implemented and then you know if my
brain is is trying to abstrac eyes
things then I can start see yeah yeah so
this this is what you were talking about
before yeah so it's there's Dual Purpose
to actually learning those actual those
actual V types and and seeing how
they're implemented yeah yeah and also I
feel that when learning those V type you
don't need to learn all of them right
right ahead before starting to try to
find them I feel like you you need to
pick one the the most fun one right the
one you are resonating with and you just
going to to understand like in depth
what are the edge cases of those
techniques let let's for instance speak
ssrf ssrf really uh pretty much W spread
came in the top 10 new o as top 10 and
uh and there is like so many fixes uh
that that are wide on the internet like
if you if you just try to go type on
internet how to fix ssrf as a developer
right you are going to see all the fixes
and you are like what the developer must
have implemented first yeah you know and
so you learn those edge cases and that's
where you come back to the IFC that
you've learned before and you're like
okay so what is an IP what is a domain
name how can I bypass uh the fixes and
you go so in Niche that you can just try
to just concentrate on that Niche until
you get sick of it and then you go to
the other
vulnerability and I think Kevin M did
for me he's one of uh the the the best
um trajectory in
backy right now I I feel like there is
some other amazing people like uh rotak
or Matan that are doing like an amazing
job on their trajectory and Kevin is one
of them where he took xss right everyone
is is taking xss as as a beginner
friendly V somehow right uh he took xss
and it wasn't like I'm going to find
like reflected acccess on all the ends
I'm going to check the biggest
implementation of dumb xss like fix and
I'm going to be specialized on how to
bypass this
implementation and then he went to learn
how to bypass D purify this is bit more
research right but the he had to learn
so many stuff like I talked with him
about that like he had to learn the IC
he had to learn how to read the is
massive too right like you see this with
the just moving into talking about
specialization you see this with Alex
Chapman right with the head browser
stuff um you know Mizu with the with the
D purify sort of aspect Johan with the
CSP related stuff right you become the
the go-to person for this specific uh
problem or this specific stack and yeah
I mean I think Alex was saying that a
almost all of his bugs this year were
collabs and he's crushing all of his
goals just because people are like okay
here's rce you know but I can't
implement it because I don't know how to
do you know V8 uh you know binary
exploitation
and he kind of bridges that Gap it's
that's that specialization piece is
really nasty if you can Master it yeah
and you don't need to over specialize
it's just maybe about going in outside
the comfort zone of the other people
right like you are in bugman competing
against the knowledge of everyone else
that is is hacking on the same Target
right and so there have a limit to to
the knowledge especially if they they're
hacking generally as a checkbox right
and so you go to your xss vulnerability
and you're like oh I I don't want to
find reflective xss I just want to find
dumb xss and then in dumb xss you're
like oh I just want to find post message
based xss and just this is like a second
layer of abstraction but just post
message xss is a bit widespread uh
currently and so if you take doability
by like what is the the the the nichest
way to exploit it and you just try to
find that as the beginning you'll find
way more uh vulnerabilities in my in my
opinion that if you try to learn
everything and hack in a general manner
do you think you should do that after or
before you've sort of covered the
general basics of all the vulnerability
classes I think uh it depends on how
much fun you're having right uh this is
the the hacking mindset to go deep and
deep into uh the rabbit hole and so if
if if you don't like SQL injection don't
go learn SQL injection that hate SQL
injection yeah I don't I don't really
like it I'm not it feels good I mean
it's a good vulnerability when you get
your hands on it but I'm not passionate
about it you know yeah I'm I'm yeah it's
not like something I enjoy searching but
I I do uh for instance enjoy enjoy
searching uh
for the dependency confusion for any
soft Supply attacks but I I I was in my
I don't need I need to stop talking just
about
that all I can think about is supply
chain no because it has been like
something I'm you've done graphel dos
you've done you know lots of other
vulnerability typ well exactly graphel
like this is like a technology that is
pretty much in every major companies and
you can find like some graph somewhere
right and there is like so much of an
attack surface on graph K Alone by
default that if you have fun learning
just graph go just for graphql but you
need
to understand if what you are doing
there will be a payoff to that if your
goal is to not just have fun but also
have the financial reward you need to
say hey that obscure technology or that
obscure Niche
vulnerability how much of that I can
really find what do we think are the top
if we had the list right now the top
high value things for a beginner to dive
deep into what's what are some of the
ones that come to you I mean graphql is
a great one I think graphql is still
very wide widely applicable you just
messaged mentioned uh post message xss I
think that's big WordPress Technologies
yeah WordPress are still uh pretty big I
I feel any framework or CMS with special
V abilities for instance if you like to
hack on
Rails uh there is like an interesting
attack surface that is just real
specific right uh so any framework uh
may maybe even libraries uh f d purify
is library right but the attack surface
of D purifier is gigantic there is like
a dum purify maybe in every react front
end that I've seen so far uh not every
but like I mean pretty much anything
that has any sort of developer um base
in it right like you're allowing the
user to be also a developer with your
tool needs to have some sort of piece of
that an advice that I can give maybe to
bug hunters and that I feel it's a good
idea tell me if it's a good idea is
instead of messaging all the top hunters
or the one that are successful in what
they're doing because they're receiving
hundred of DMS go message a developer of
the technology you are trying to to hack
like someone on ledin they're pretty
responsive man to be honest like at
least that's been my experience just
kind of talking to these people that are
passionate about these projects yeah Ju
Just if you you want to act on reals do
go talk with a res developer and just
ask them like how do you implement your
code you don't need to really know how
to code a raise application in order to
hack it you just need to at least
understand the fundamentals like the
abstract of it and so just ask hey
what's your developer life cycle uh when
you deploy such application and then try
to think okay that's how he's doing it
so I need to have pack it that way um
and and I think that's like a good piece
of advice like if you go Niche try to be
part of the ecosystem that you are
targeting like if you are hacking on
WordPress go follow some WordPress
developers go follow uh the the the the
discussion uh if there change logs the
get get some data feeds for those yeah
Ju Just go into the developer Community
because they are the one producing the
viabilities like you're top Hunter like
like for forance you when I message you
you are not producing any viabilities
you are finding them but the guys that
like the people that have PR those VES
are just out there right and they are
talking publicly and you can go learn
from them their mistakes right and I
think I've learned more talking to
developer about code revieww stuff than
actually to hackers yeah man there there
have been some really crazy times the
live hacking events where I'll I'll come
up to the developers on like the first
day and I'll be like hey if you were
going to search for vs in this code base
where would you look and and sometimes
they they'll be like uh you know screw
off like you know I'm not going to tell
you that you know but sometimes they'll
be like oh you know I really think this
is sketchy right and and I just remember
one live hacking event where I did that
and it was just so sketchy the whole
area that they pointed me to and I found
like 15 bugs on that and I was like man
that was a really good call Ben Ben
taught me that that actually um that
trick and I and for the people that
don't have access to liveing events like
more beginner people like just talk with
with with some people on the internet
that are actually developing the those
Technologies like uh there is like in
web hacking there is some discords there
is some forums there's some Twitter
accounts uh and and that that I think
could be quite responsive yeah just
going back to the like what niches could
be good right now um I I think there's
an area for somebody who is a gadget
master like somebody who really just
builds automation solely around
collecting non vulnerability gadgets you
know like like let's say I need a some
ability to redirect on this specific
Target right it doesn't even necessarily
to be an open it could be a semiopen it
could be you know whatever I just need
some ability to redirect on a Target
having that you know around I need a CSP
bypass that's on this specific domain I
need you know a cookie set Gadget you
know around right it's having somebody
who
their specialty their Niche could be
collecting those gadgets and then
working with the community to to fill
the needs of various exploits and you
kind of see that with Eric right Eric
does that to a to a certain extent but I
think he focuses more on gadgets that
are also vulnerabilities rather than
gadgets that are not vulnerabilities in
and of themselves uh local storage um uh
if you're able to like poison or
invalidate some data in local storage
right that could be that could be a
gadget those sort of things could be
interesting um maybe also SSO uh
anything related that's a good one yeah
openconnect uh
implementations uh that that one's crazy
actually yeah if you master that that
would be really cool yeah and I I feel
that um this is more like a developer
implementation and that
you you don't really need to learn that
much of HTTP to be able to at least find
some viabilities just know saml like s
if you just Master Sam alone I feel like
that would be and and we've seen that
actually there's a hacker that's going
to come on in the Pod at some point when
the vulnerabilities that he wants to
talk about have been uh patched um I
mean somebody there's somebody who does
that and I think there's room for more
of those as well yeah uh the the
principle if you want to go to to a
niche is like your Niche should be a
niche of expertise but not a niche of
implementation right because there is
some people that Focus like on a
technology that is used Maybe by maybe
100 company in the world uh right and
there is some bigger technologies that
no one has a security expertise on and
that is not I would say not too hard to
build it uh right uh for instance you
can focus solely on
laral uh laral is getting bigger bigger
every year and I feel that there is like
a huge PHP community in security that is
targeting it but not that much bu
Hunters right that could be an is right
because widely implemented but not
enough expertise or Ison yeah we we we
see we've seen the ticket trick stuff
before right when you're focusing on
these sort of ticketing systems um one
of the things that I've and this is sort
of related to The Post message exess
because most of those are actually
implemented you know a lot of the post
message XS occur in these sort of
gadgets but I think uh a lot of times
you'll see on like the www or on like
the marketing website for a specific
company you'll see these like little
chat Bots that are meant to you know
connect you to a salesperson or like
help Provide support or whatever and uh
a lot of times these are implemented
just by dropping a Javascript file onto
the main site and uh then they need to
communicate back to their you know main
their iframe or like their main server
in some capacity so you see the post
message stuff there I think those things
are riddled with vulnerabilities and I
have a couple zero days actually I need
to talk to people about how to spray in
those specific plugins common ones yeah
but and this is like depend depending on
how much knowledge you have uh how you
will approach those niches but I don't
think you need to be like a really like
really an expert before diving into a
niche as I said when I started buben
hunting I just tried to find any
viabilities in
WordPress plugins that's a mish right uh
but because WordPress is so much
implemented there is so much plugins
there will be a lot of it's a reflection
of the rest of the ecosystem too in the
WordPress environment piece right like
like you know sure WordPress plugins you
know you get the source code and stuff
like that which is not something you you
you see always but they're vulnerable to
the same sort of thing as other things
right C surf you know xss sqli if you're
lucky you know that sort of thing um so
especially those niches that are
reflections of the bigger system as a
whole and when I was trying to find
vulnerabilities on WordPress plugins I
was just concentrating on xss it was
just so so it's w you weren even looking
at the other own types no no no if if I
it was obvious to me as a beginner I was
like okay I'm going to to search for it
but not everything was obvious to me
when I was a beginner right and so but s
that I understood that I was excess and
so I was like okay I'm going to find xss
on those plugins and if I don't find
anything in the plugin I will go to
another Target and do that again until
that one day I didn't have any more
targets or any more plugins and I was
like okay let's try a new
approach yeah absolutely man yeah lots
of lots of niches to be explored I I'm
trying to Rack my brain it's late it's
getting late here so I'm not uh not much
left in there for racking but uh
definitely tons of niches I'm interested
to hear what the community drops in the
comments as well and like interaction on
on Twitter afterwards because there's
always like you know whenever we talk
about these sort of segments people
always are like ah you know what about
this what about that I think that'll be
I think that'll be helpful for the for
the community I think if it's possible
for the beginners like uh watching the
podcast or uh maybe on the comments or
on Twitter to tell us like what was the
hardest part of learning web hacking or
what what is the current struggle
because and I'm not talking like about
finding a Target or anything it's just
about like really the core knowledge
what is it for them right now because I
in my opinion again when I was a
beginner I hit so many so many
walls and the only struggle that I
really had was the motivation right like
it was the resilency that when I was
hitting a
wall What could I do to you know
overcome the obstacle and that
motivation was like my main struggle uh
but I know there is some other struggles
that are more like on the technical side
and less on The Human Side and I think
it would be cool to know what are those
and how like people can facilitate them
what what was your biggest uh success in
overcoming that motivation
piece it's when I found like for me it
was when I found my my Niche right like
my when I created a comfort zone that
was outside of other outside of the
other people comfort zone but where I
felt like I had the expertise right now
on that subject do you think that was
because you were experiencing success or
do you think that that was because you
respected yourself as a
hacker I think it's because I had an
hypothesis and hypotheses were getting
trer and truer and so I got confidence
into what I was doing so probably more
success yeah I I I I I feel so like I'm
I'm the that part of uh I would say the
the researcher security research
community that I can't say that I'm a
really hacker because you need to say uh
yeah you know like originally to say
that you a hacker you need that other
people to say that you are a hacker
right and because hacker is your Nar is
like what you want to become and this is
something that you always need to grow
uh and trying to evolve right and I feel
that sometime we forget that we are not
at the top of our field and our
knowledge and that we need to go further
so I'm not considering myself as a
hicker because I want to One Day become
like a true lead hacker yeah you you
always got this this moving picture of
like what the ideal is is that what
you're saying yeah exactly and and
that's what drives me that motivates me
is that uh one day I can grasp the idea
of being a hacker uh and I feel
that yeah again that's depend on your
goal like if do you want to become a
hacker do you want to become a Bug
Hunter a security researcher like you
need to figure out that and create
motivation around that I think we have
to hack the motivation as well that's
one of the things that I kind of talk
about with the with did you say hack the
motivation yeah yeah you got to hack the
motivation as well you want to hack
everything right I mean you got to right
I mean because at the end of the day
that's one of the biggest challenges and
I think one of the things that I say
about hacking the motivation is you know
identifying when you're making progress
even though it doesn't feel like
progress when you're covering end points
when you're finding gadgets those are
all progress and I think as a beginner
as you're starting one of the nice
things about having like a checklist or
whatever is like okay I can check off
this little piece and I can say okay
well you know I am making some progress
here whether it's in your learning
curriculum or whether it's in you know
your actual assessment saying okay well
I've assessed this target for xss on
this one end point you know that's
progress and and I you know you you
trust that that progress or that
progression
is a part of validating your hypothesis
on whether this this whole process will
get you to the point of you know finding
a vulnerability or being a hacker
whatever you want to whatever you want
to delegate as your actual end goal um
and then you know if it doesn't just
like you do when you're hacking you have
to adjust your hypoth hthis and say okay
well maybe this isn't really how it
works right and then and then you
construct a new hypothesis and you keep
on keep on pushing with that so you do
abstra abstract thinking yeah yeah I can
do abstract I can do abstract thinking
I'm not an abstract we just cycling back
to that like to the fact that you need
to think on another layer and that I
feel that's the M the real entry point
of actually starting your backb career
even if you're like I really an expert
of insecurity
or like a beginner in everything is that
your ability
into thinking differently than just what
is in front of you right if that makes
sense I don't know if you have like a
better wording for that no I mean I
think that makes sense yeah I think
you've got to think um you know you
could say think outside of the box it's
a bit of a of a cliche but um yeah
trying to pop up that extra layer right
it's almost like one of those techniques
you you implement in in meditation right
like I remember like closing my eyes and
trying to focus on you know my breathing
or whatever and then the the coach the
meditation coach or whatever would say
like oh you know you're going to have
these thoughts come to your mind and you
make sure you don't like you know push
that you know get too upset with
yourself when that actually happens you
just kind of have the thought and then
you just you pop right out of the
thought and go one layer higher and I
think you can go one layer higher or you
can go one layer lower um in hacking and
you can see results on on both sides of
those yeah it's like walking the path
and visualizing the path that you are
going to walk like this is two different
things and two different ways of hacking
dude you think we're high right now you
know we're sitting here like yeah man
it's like all of hacking is like a cloud
and you just pop out of it I feel that
metaphors really helps though yeah you
think so okay well that that makes one
of
us all right man you want to wrap it
there yeah let's go all right that
sounds good thanks for coming on dude
yeah thanks a lot
peace and that's a wrap on this episode
of critical thinking thanks so much for
listening and if you want more critical
thinking content head over to ctbb show/
Discord join the Discord there's lots of
great conversations and chats going on
over there and if you want to support
the show there's the Discord subscriber
tiers which give you access to master
classes amas hack alongs exclusive
scripts and an exclusive chat Channel
with us we'll see you there
[Music]